<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="eng" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Pesindon I and II (914-08-14)</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>EpiDoc Encoding</resp>
          <persName ref="part:tykd">
            <name>Tyassanti Kusumo Dewanti</name>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
          <persName ref="part:tykd">
            <name>Tyassanti Kusumo Dewanti</name>
          </persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>DHARMA</authority>
        <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
        <idno type="filename">DHARMA_INS04Pesindon</idno>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
            <p>Copyright © 2019-2025 by Tyassanti Kusumo Dewanti.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <msIdentifier>
            <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
            <idno/>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
            <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <handDesc>
              <p/>
            </handDesc>
          </physDesc>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The project DHARMA has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <schemaRef key="EGDv01" type="guide" url="https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-02888186"/>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="bib" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9\-\_]+)" replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/1633743/erc-dharma/items/tag/$1">
          <p>Public URIs with the prefix bib to point to a Zotero Group Library named ERC-DHARMA whose data are open to the public.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="part" matchPattern="([a-z]+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml#$1">
          <p>Internal URIs using the part prefix to point to person elements in the <ref>DHARMA_IdListMembers_v01.xml</ref> file.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change status="draft" when="2023" who="part:mime">Initial encoding of the inscription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:space="preserve">
    <body>
      <!--
No other visual documentation of these plates is available than the aforementioned facsimile. Facing the impossibility of inspecting the original plates and the ambiguity presented by this facsimile, we reluctantly decided to adopt the numbering according to the facsimile in Holle (1879), which is already applied by Damais (1955). The edition presented below is based on Damais’ edition, controlled by the facsimiles in Holle (1879) and Kern (1917).
The justification for Damais’ decision to follow the facsimile in Holle (1879) is explained in Damais 1952: 52, n.1: “Nous n’avons pas consulté les plaques originales au Musée de Djakarta et nous ne connaissons pas de photographies, mais il est certain que le fac-similé de l’article de Holle dans <foreign>TBG</foreign>, 25, 1879, face à la page 464 est plus près de l’original.” English translation is as follows: “We have not consulted the original plates in the Jakarta Museum and are not aware of any photographs, but it is certain that the facsimile of Holle’s article in TBG, 25, 1879, page 464 is closer to the original”.
-->
      <div type="edition" xml:lang="kaw-Latn">
        <p>
<!-- Plate I (silver) -->
<lb n="1r1"/> // svaṣti śaka-varsātĭta <num value="836">836</num> śrăvana-măsa tiṭhi pacammi
<lb n="1r2"/> kr̥ṣna-pakṣa tu po Ā vāra tatkā<supplied reason="omitted">la</supplied> ḍaṁ hyaṁ guru sivi-
<lb break="no" n="1r3"/> ta sumoce Avak·nira, plat· bvas· saha rabi sakalan·ḍu, kanyā /
<!-- Plate II (gold) -->
<lb n="1r1"/> // svaśti śaka-varsătĭta <num value="836">836</num> śrăvana-mă-
<lb break="no" n="1r2"/> śa tiṭhi pacami kr̥ṣṇa-pakṣa tu po Ā
<lb n="1r3"/> vāra tatkā<supplied reason="omitted">la</supplied> ḍaṁ hyaṁ gu<add place="below">ru</add> sivita sumoce
<lb n="1r4"/> Avak·nira, <unclear>plat</unclear>· bvas·, saha rabi sakala<surplus>ṁ</surplus>ḍu, kanyā /
</p>
      </div>
      <div type="apparatus">
        <!-- The siglum K refers to Kern’s edition and the siglum D refers to Damais’. -->
        <!-- Plate I (silver) -->
        <app loc="1r1">
          <lem>836</lem>
          <note>D, 826 K. Damais (1955: 50), said that from epigraphical and calendrical point of view, it is impossible to accept Kern’s reading. After having calculated and converted it to the CE year, Damais concluded that the number for the tens must be read as 3. When we refer to the <foreign>Tableau comparatif des chiffres indonésiens</foreign> (Damais 1952: 107), the figure for the units in two inscriptions dating to 823 (Kayu Ara Hiwang and Rongkab), the shape of the 3 is quite similar to what we have in the two Pesindon plates, which were the source for Damais’ specimen of 3 in that table.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r1">
          <lem>tiṭhi</lem>
          <note>K, tithi D.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r1">
          <lem>pacammi</lem>
          <note>corr. pañcami.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r2">
          <lem>tatkā<supplied reason="omitted">la</supplied></lem>
          <note>tatkā K, tatkāla D. Kern, left a note just after <foreign>tatkā</foreign>, “d.i. <foreign>tatkāla”.</foreign></note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r3">
          <lem>bvas</lem>
          <note>K, br̥s D.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r3">
          <lem>sakalan·ḍu, kanyā</lem>
          <note>K, sakalan·ḍukanyā D. In the 1917 facsimile, a stroke that might be a punctuation mark is present.</note>
        </app>
        <!-- Plate II (gold) -->
        <app loc="1r1">
          <lem>svaśti</lem>
          <note>K, svasti D.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r1">
          <lem>836</lem>
          <note>D, 826 K.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r2">
          <lem>tiṭhi</lem>
          <note>K, tithi D.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r2">
          <lem>pacami</lem>
          <note>corr. pañcami.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r3">
          <lem>tatkā<supplied reason="omitted">la</supplied></lem>
          <note>tatkā K, tatkāla D. Kern did not leave the same comment as he did previously for this word in the first plate. Possibly because he was thinking that the remark should be regarded as applicable to both cases.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r4">
          <lem>
            <unclear>plat</unclear>
          </lem>
          <note>[..]lat D, plǝt K.</note>
        </app>
        <app loc="1r4">
          <lem>sakala<surplus>ṁ</surplus>ḍu, kanyā</lem>
          <note>sakalaṁ ḍu, kanyā K, sakalaṁḍukanyā D. We omit the <foreign>anusvāra </foreign>and the punctuation mark to conform the reading of the first plate. In the 1917 facsimile, the <foreign>anusvāra </foreign>does not appear though.</note>
        </app>
      </div>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
        <p>Hail! Elapsed Śaka year 836, month of Śravana, fifth <foreign>tithi </foreign>of the waning fortnight, Tuṅlai, Pon, Sunday. It was the time that the venerable master (<foreign>ḍaṅ hyaṅ guru</foreign>) Siwita cleaned away his body, his stiff sexual organ (<foreign>plat bvas</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>together with (his) spouse (called) Sakalaṇḍu [and their] daughter(s).</p>
      </div>
      <div type="commentary">
        <p>1r2 <foreign>daṅ hyaṅ guru</foreign> Sivita only appears in the other plate, Pesindon II (1r3), but not elsewhere. We translate it as the venerable master, while Sarkar has “the spiritual teacher”. The title <foreign>daṅ hyaṅ guru</foreign> is found in Mandang I (Sucen I) and Mangulihi B. Both of those inscriptions come from the north area of Central Java. Mandang was found in <foreign>desa </foreign>Kandangan, <foreign>kabupaten </foreign>Temanggung. As for the later inscription, the find spot was in the Wonosobo area. An East Java inscription, Dinaya II, also has <foreign>daṅ hyaṅ guru </foreign>(line 2).</p>
        <p>For the editions, see NBG 1888: 21–22, Sarkar 1971–72, vol. I: 14–15 (no. XV), Boechari 1985–86: 203.</p>
        <p>For the editions, see Damais 1955: 206.</p>
        <p>1r3 The word <foreign>sumoce </foreign>is not recorded in OJED. It might be a verb that comes from the word <foreign>śoca </foreign>or <foreign>śuci</foreign>, whose meaning revolves around the idea of cleanliness and purity. Although in OJED, there is no indication of purification with fire, in his translation, Kern supposed that the context evokes the idea of ablutions, cleansing the body with fire and leaving the mundane life on earth (Kern 1917: 15). Sarkar commented on Kern’s notion that “The interpretation is not fully warranted by the data. It is just possible that they took ablutions or did other purificatory rites in a holy place and then went to their own quarters” (Sarkar 1971–72, vol. II: 144, n. 19).</p>
        <p>1r3 The meaning of <foreign>plat bvas </foreign>is hard to understand. Here, we think about <foreign>plat </foreign>as a registered word in OJED, meaning “male sexual organ” and <foreign>bvas </foreign>as <foreign>bos</foreign>, which in OJED is listed as “sullen, surly? stern, stiff?”. Kern seems to have another point of view for this expression, as could be seen from his remark: “<foreign>plǝt</foreign> (of <foreign>plat) bvas</foreign>. Denkelijk eene zelfde uitdrukking als b.v. ’t Jav. <foreign>mak blǝs</foreign> [zooveel als ons «pang, weg!»]; plat is eene variatie van <foreign>plas</foreign>, en <foreign>bvas</foreign> van <foreign>blas</foreign>, in vorm gelijk <foreign>bos</foreign> (<foreign>jǝbos, bus</foreign>); plat bvas geeft «in eens weggaan» te kennen.” (Kern 1917: 15, n.1) To sum up, he was thinking of an onomatopoeic expression which is expressive of the personages “going away” or “departing somewhere” at a fast pace. That understanding was adopted by Sarkar in his translation (1971–72, vol. II: 144). Wisseman Christie’s translation goes into different direction, since she opt the reading of <foreign>br̥s </foreign>rather than <foreign>bvas</foreign>. That term was analyzed by her as a derivation from the Sanskrit word <foreign>vr̥sa</foreign>, meaning “husband, man, bull, the most excellent” and also the other epithet for Siwa as the procreator.</p>
        <p>The english translation is as follows: “<foreign>plǝt</foreign> (or <foreign>plat)</foreign> <foreign>bvas</foreign>. Probably the same expression as e.g. the jav. <foreign>mak blǝs</foreign> [as much as our “bang, gone!”]; <foreign>plat</foreign> is a variation of <foreign>plas</foreign>, and <foreign>bvas</foreign> of <foreign>blas</foreign>, similar in form to <foreign>bos</foreign> (<foreign>jǝbos, bus</foreign>); <foreign>plat bvas</foreign> indicates “go away at once”.</p>
        <p>1r3 The last phrase of this short inscription (1r4 in the second plate), which both plates read as<foreign> saha rabi sakalanḍu, kanyā </foreign>is very unusual and difficult to discern. All possibilities that come to mind still raise some problems. We try to deduct and think of these three points:</p>
        <p>There is a connection with the Sanskrit word <foreign>sakala </foreign>(all) and <foreign>duḥkha </foreign>(misfortune) and the text intended to say something like ‘cleaned away (<foreign>sumoce</foreign>)... all misfortune’.</p>
        <p>What comes after <foreign>rabi </foreign>is considered as a personal name. The name Sakalaṇḍu, whatever weird it may sound, to our mind is harking back to the name of <foreign>dyah </foreign>Salaḍū. The whole sequence then can mean ”daughter of Sakalaṇdu” or “wife Sakalaṇḍu [and their] daugther(s)”.</p>
        <p>We may have a word <foreign>laṇḍuh </foreign>(uninterrupted, prosperous) or its other form <foreign>makalaṇḍuhan</foreign> (in peace and prosperity). But this seems hard to fit in the context rather than the two previous points.</p>
        <p>At this present state of knowledge, we opt for the second point. Translations given by other scholars are also varied, as they also read it differently. Kern translated it as “with his wife (or wives) and <foreign>guṇḍik</foreign>’s”. He took the word <foreign>sakalaṅ</foreign> and <foreign>ḍukanyā </foreign>separately, which for the first word, he understood it as meaning “all”, and the latter means the girl(s). As for Sarkar, he understood <foreign>sakalaṅ </foreign>as “all” and remarked the morpheme <foreign>ḍu</foreign> as it might stand for <foreign>ḍua</foreign>, i.e. “two”. Therefore his translation becomes “all (his) wives and two daughters”. Wisseman Christie, however, took the <foreign>sakalaṅ </foreign>as the Saskrit term <foreign>sakala</foreign>, meaning “in visible, material form, embodied”. Her translation reads “together with his wife, embodied in visible form (<foreign>sakala</foreign>) at that time.</p>
        <p>Kern 1917: 15. The Dutch version is as follows: “.. met zijn vrouw (of vrouwen) en <foreign>guṇḍik</foreign>’s.”</p>
        <p>See Kern 1917: 15 (n. 2 and n. 3). The English translation for n.2: “<foreign>sakalaṅ</foreign> = “all” (cf. Malay) takes the <foreign>ṅ</foreign> as a number concept; <foreign>n</foreign> is the change of <foreign>ṅ</foreign> for a subsequent lingual or dental; according to correct spelling it had to be a <foreign>ṇ</foreign>; in like manner <foreign>piṅḍo</foreign> has passed into <foreign>piṇḍo</foreign>, often spelled <foreign>pinḍo</foreign>.” The English translation for n.3: “<foreign>ḍukanyā</foreign> (<foreign>ḍu. kanya</foreign>) no doubt contains<foreign> ḍuk</foreign>= Jav. <foreign>hǝṇḍuk</foreign> (girl), of which <foreign>gǝṇḍuk</foreign> is a variation. A finer pronunciation, a kind of krama of <foreign>gǝnduk</foreign> is <foreign>guṇḍik</foreign>. —The question remains, however, whether<foreign> ḍukanya</foreign> is solvable <foreign>ukan</foreign>, which may be a plural of <foreign>ḍuk</foreign>, and <foreign>nya</foreign>, “his”; or that ḍukanya is a conjunction of a Old Javanese and Sanskrit word, which means as the same thing, viz. <foreign>ḍuk</foreign> and <foreign>kanyā</foreign>, “girl”. The little mark between <foreign>ḍu</foreign> and<foreign> k</foreign> makes me suspect the latter. It, however, does not change the meaning.”</p>
      </div>
      <div type="bibliography">
        <p>The sigla Br and Na refer to Brandes’ and Nakada’s editions, respectively. In view of the fact that the fifth section was read by Kern and Nakada, both of them yielding rather different readings, for this part I use the siglum K, which stands for Kern. </p>
        <listBibl type="primary">
          <bibl n="siglum"/>
          <!-- one <bibl/> per item of primary bibliography. Every entry mentionned in apparatus  should hava a @n to declare its sigla -->
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl type="secondary">
          <bibl/>
          <!-- one <bibl/> per item of secondary bibliography -->
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
