<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hampran</title>
            <!--Change the title of the file, e.g. Raktamālā grant of the time of Budhagupta, year 159-->
            <!-- Add your name in the respStmt matching your involvement -->
            <respStmt>
               <resp>EpiDoc encoding</resp>
               <resp>Intellectual authorship of edition</resp>
               <persName ref="part:argr">
                  <forename>Arlo</forename>
                  <surname>Griffiths</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA <note>This project has received funding from the European Research
						Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and
						innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</note>
            </authority>
            <pubPlace>Lyon</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">Hampran</idno>
            <!-- Replace by filename, e.g. Pallava00001 -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported
							Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit
							https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to
							Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View,
							California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Arlo Griffiths.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><!-- only the handDesc can be filled in at this stage -->
            <msDesc><!-- //// NB: the msIdentifier had to be added for validation purposes ///. It will be edited later with the metadata spreadsheet -->
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>DHARMAbase</repository>
                  <idno/>
                  <!-- don't modify this -->
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents><!-- describe the intellectual content of an inscription -->
                  <summary><!-- //// NOT MANDATORY  ////--></summary>
                  <!-- offers the possibility to give a summary of the inscription's content -->
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <p>Similarity to Balekambang inscription.</p>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:argr" when="2020-04-01">Initial encoding of the inscription</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div type="edition" xml:lang="san-Latn">
            <!--edition encoded as per EG §§2−7-->
(A1) // śrīr astu svasti prajābhyaḥ śakakālātīta 673 | 5 | 2 (1/2) | ? ? (ra)vā-
(A2) ra maddhyāh(naṁ) // ⊙

<lg n="1" met="sragdharā">
<lb n="B1"/> // dharmmārthaṁ kṣetradānaṁ yad udayajananaṁ yo dadātīśabhaktyā ⚬
(B2) hampragrāmaṁ trigo(ṣ)ṭhyā mahitam anumataṁ (s)iddhadevyāś ca tasyāḥ
(B3) kośāmragrāvalekhākṣaravidhividitaprāntasīmāvidhānam·
(B4) tasyaitad bhānunāmno bhuvi bhavatu yaśojīvita(ṁ c)aiva nityaṁ</lg>
(B5) about 7 illegible akṣaras, possibly in much later script

(Ca) between the figures I and II: R̥ṣi
(Cb) between II and III: prā .....
(Cc) between III and IV: unreadable
(Cd) between IV and V: ji ......
(Ce) to the right of V: ka


         </div>
         <div type="apparatus">
           <!--apparatus encoded as per EG §9.1, basic elements for apparatus below-->
               <listApp><!-- one <app> for each apparatus entry -->
                  <app loc="line"><!-- update the value of @loc.-->
                     <lem><!-- fill in a lemma here --></lem>
                     <rdg source="bib:AuthorYear_01"><!-- update the @source value, fill in variant reading here --></rdg>
                  </app>
               </listApp>
         </div>
         <div type="translation">
 	<p>ranslation
	A. Let there be fortune! Hail to the people! Elapsed Śaka era 674 ... mid-day.
	B. The gift of arable land that he gives for the sake of dharma, out of devotion for Īśa (Śiva); that promotes prosperity, being praised by the Triple Assembly (trigoṣṭhyā)* and accepted by its Siddhadevī: the village Hampran, for which the arrangement of the outer boundary markers is known from an ordinance in the form of a stone inscription (grāva-lekha) (at) Kośāmra (i.e., at Poh)** — may it and the life of the fame of this one called Bhānu be eternal here on earth!”
	C. (untranslateable)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="commentary">
            <!--commentary encoded as per section §9.3 -->
         </div>
        <div type="bibliography">
	<!--bibliography encoded as per section §9.4 -->
	<!-- NB: you are encouraged to experiment with encoding bibliography to the extent you have the bibliographic data available, but it is not mandatory at this stage, because our bibliographic data are normally assembled along with other metadata in spreadsheets and will be imported from there into our xml files by a semi-automated process at a later stage. -->
           <p>This inscription was first edited by J.G. de Casparis, in his Inscripties uit de Çailendra-tijd (Prasasti Indonesia, vol. I, 1951), p. 9. I inspected it in situ on 26 April 2009 and again on 16 August 2011, and revisited the site again on 20 December 2012 to make the estampage that is now kept as n. 2308 at the EFEO in Paris. The inscription is surrounded by a frame engraved into the stone, delimited by a horizontal bar at ca. 2/3 of the height. The part above the bar is further divisible in two due to a deep and presumably old crack in the stone to which a division in the text corresponds. The three horizontal planes are here called A, B and C. Plane C comprises five yantras (in the shape of squares with flower petals extending from each side) engraved into the stone, here called a, b, c, d, e, with some akṣaras interspersed. De Casparis (p. X) provides a drawing of this plane C. About De Casparis’ reading of the text it is useful to cite from Damais’ review (BEFEO 54 [1968], p. 315):

« On est étonné que la transcription ne présente aucun aksara incertain alors que plusieurs sont d'une forme inusuelle et quelquefois incompréhensible. Malgré les explications données à ce sujet par l’auteur (p. 2-3) et une seule note à propos de la syllabe qu’il transcrit si (siddha dewyāś du 2e vers), la transcription ne donne pas une idée suffisante des difficultés d’interprétation de plusieurs aksara. Le si que nous venons de citer est en particulier tellement aberrant qu’il s'agit en fait non pas d’une lecture, mais d’une restitution. »

The Indonesian scholar Poerbatjaraka has published a reading of his own. A short notice citing one new reading was presented by Damais in BEFEO 50.2 (1962), p. 461f.: « L’auteur donne une transcription légèrement différente de certains mots de l’inscription de Hampran, publiée pour la première fois par De Casparis. Il nie par ailleurs le caractère bouddhique que De Casparis attribue à ce document et considère qu’il s’agit d’une inscription śiwaïte, Īśa étant un nom de Śiwa et sans rapport avec le Buddha. Une de ses nouvelles lectures étant Trigaṣṭhi [sic], il y voit un synonyme de Triśālā, qui serait à l’origine de la ville bien connue au Centre de Java, Sålåtigå, à quelques kilomètres de l’endroit où a été trouvée l’inscription en question dont le nom serait une indonésianisation du terme sanskrit. Il termine en discutant la personnalité de Śrī Bhānu. Les nouvelles lectures de certains mots de l’inscription demandant une étude serrée, nous y reviendrons à une autre occasion. »  As far as I know, Damais never was able to return to the new readings.

Re-edited here from estampage on 6 March 2020. Doutbful passages are marked in red.
</p>
        	<listBibl type="primary">
				<bibl/><!-- one <bibl/> per item of primary bibliography -->
			</listBibl>
           <listBibl type="secondary">
              <bibl/><!-- one <bibl/> per item of secondary bibliography -->
           </listBibl>
        </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
